so I'll just read out the question to
quote you from the last session I don't
really care that much about how the
Federal Reserve works because it's going
away really quick so that's true who or
what is going to replace things like
that not specifically the Federal
Reserve but think of it in the abstract
like things like that there's sort of
systems gonna replace them and do you
know groups that are actually working on
those problems specifically well we can
talk about that thinking maybe two
languages so I'll talk about it in mmm
this way to put this shenanigans all
right there we go so there's one
approach to alternate call shenanigans
there lots of shenanigans going on
that's that's one answer to the question
those are folks who are in positions of
power folks in positions of power
looking at the current Federal Reserve
structure and you learn awesome this
looks fantastic I see something I can
make very pliable and then up gradient
the kinds of things I'd like to see and
we've already seen that like right now
the thing that we used to call the
Federal Reserve guess what it's gone I
don't know you guys know but the changes
that were made in the past couple of
days so radically change the nature of
that construct that it's called the Fed
Reserve in name only and those are
serious shenanigans like that is a
massive change the underlying financial
structure of this country so check it's
over shenanigans done that is over folks
who are trying to work some shenanigans
to show will ask what happened to the
Fed oh well just do a little brief it
doesn't take too much energy so the
Federal Reserve is very very limited in
the kinds of things that's allowed to do
by the way it's actual amended its
miniscule compared to what it's been
doing recently but most fundamentally it
can only operate through a very small
number of primary lenders these big
banks the too big to fail banks the
reason why they're too big to fail is
because they're the way the Federal
Reserve hits the real economy so if they
failed the head of the Federal Reserve
would have no interface with the real
economy and they could only engage in a
very small number of kinds of
transactions with them it could take we
called repo actions this is going to
give very esoteric very quick but some
time not long ago like three four days
ago a complete restructure has put in
place where a series of things that are
called special purpose vehicles were
created managed by a private firm called
Blackrock which is the world's largest
asset manager and direct interface to
the United States Treasury which to the
US Treasury now is able to and on the
hook for put in Treasuries which is the
kind of assets that Fed can count as
being real things into these specialist
special-purpose vehicles the SPV s can
then use those assets to acquire almost
any kind of financial security which is
safe equities like shares and companies
and what's called corporate paper so
bonds and companies put them on the
books of the special-purpose vehicles
and the Treasury's assets are what's
called first law loser which is to say
that if the price to say an SP V buy
shares in uber an uber goes from 40 to
20 the United States Treasury takes that
loss so what that means is that as of
right now two things have changed one
the Treasury can now inject the quid aid
directly into the into the economy at
the most almost the most fundamental
level not quite down to human beings but
we're getting there real quick and the
US Treasury is actually now more or less
driving the show they're actually on the
other side of that actually being able
to pressure things and I would be very
surprised if at this point now Secretary
of Muchin and the president are not able
to actually just do the things they want
to do directly to the tune of trillions
of dollars so that's what happened to
the Fed now I would say that's a very
high quality level of shenanigans all
right now let's look on the other side
yes there are groups that are looking at
what might replace it I am associated
with some of these groups have been for
quite some time
alternatives actually look like a
radical devolution of authority and
power from the existing institutional
structures using a combination of
principles to design new models so for
example one principle is to push as much
choice making authority down to the edge
as possible so ubi it's this very simple
example and I don't mean ubi from the
point of view of means I mean ubi from
the point of view of how do you make a
functional economy actually know it we
just throw this out there let's see what
people think about it take collective
intelligence as the metaphor of the
market the market is opposed to provide
a really high-quality function of
collective intelligence I had a price
function supply and demand function
supposed to tell us stuff a whole lot of
stuff about what the very large number
of people out there are perceiving is
what is needful and are able to provide
to that to that need but we have at
least two major problems with our
collective intelligence as it exists
right now one problem is we're not
getting the right kind of signal balance
from the from the nodes now if if Bill
Gates has all the dollars then our
market is getting all of its signals
from one node now he doesn't but he has
a lot of them and every other node that
may actually have real significant
perception that it needs to inject into
that collective intelligence if it
doesn't have the right amount of signal
they were actually getting a very warped
sense of reality and so this the thing
that Piketty looked at he kind of looked
at it from the point of view of
injustice I'm going to look at it from
the point of view of a malfunctioning
sense making system we're actually not
getting the sense thinking from our
system that we're supposed to be getting
because the network topology is all
fucked up
all right well ubi is at one point one
element of that is to correct that I
need to inject an adequate amount of
signal which in this case is money and
every node to make sure I'm actually
getting signals from my entire network
if I get that then I've actually got a
network topology that is construction so
as to maximize the collective
intelligence and that just is a more
effective more powerful machine so I
don't need to have be worrying too much
about things like equity and fairness at
least not first-order I just need to be
worrying about with this thing supposed
to do and then I've got another one
there's other one I think is extremely
powerful people grasp it
this is very well known but it's
shocking how much economists don't take
it into account if I'm looking at the
the supply and demand function we know
that we have a massive cliff like a
nonlinear jump in choice making at the
threshold of privation and so if I've
got enough money that I can tell
somebody all right so somebody comes to
me and says I would like you to clean
the toilets in my office building and I
say all right well what are you willing
to offer and they say bucks an hour
my response is fuck you because I've got
fucking money
that's a terrible offer ain't willing to
do it but there's a lot of people who
can't say fuck you and the problem is in
our particular economy if you don't have
fuck you money then you've got oh I'm
about to get fucked money you just have
to say yes to whatever offer is made so
you got a whole lot of people who are
radically being underbid their the the
price signal and demand signal or
asymmetric because of this non-linearity
and the ability to say no to an offer so
by replacing people's ability to say no
to an offer you actually reestablish the
symmetry and continuity of the price and
demand function now imagine what happens
when somebody is now sitting there who's
currently being paid minimum wage to
clean the toilets and JP Morgan's office
building just says fuck you I'm just
gonna go home and plant a garden instead
then the boys of JP Morgan have to
figure out how they're gonna get their
toilets cleaned they got probably three
choices right now they can clean their
own damn toilets which is perfectly fine
or they can pay a fair wage which will
probably be in the order of like $85,000
it's just how much you have to pay me to
clean their toilets and that's that's
really actually what the price signal
should be that's how much value this
this actual work actually has if the
market was doing its job fairly that's
what you'd see then you get option three
if people are paying ninety thousand
dollars to get their toilets clean guess
what Elaan musts gonna be doing not
building electric cars he's gonna be
peeling building toilet cleaning robots
boom our economy is actually doing the
right stuff for the first time in a long
time all right if you think about ubi as
a mechanism for solving the problem of
the fact that the collective
intelligence mechanisms or markets have
actually not been functioning because
they haven't been designed appropriately
to make sure that the signal we're
getting from the pricing and demand side
is actually right then you've actually
got your head on straight if you're
designing or
economy and your finance around that
kind of thinking right it's it's just
creating a network construct that gets
the right kind of signal through the
graph the people are participating in to
get maximum collective intelligence then
you can design something that actually
works yes there are groups that are
trying to do things like that on that
basis
with any luck we and/or they will start
releasing proposals over the next couple
of weeks
because the opportunity for actually
doing is pretty high right now all right
so that's some stuff again I said a lot
of words I can go on forever about it
but it feels like hopping about seems to
be the right thing to do here yeah I
think everyone needs to invest in
toilet-cleaning rooibos I think is what
lets take away from that is find the
dirtiest job that people don't want to
do and find a way to get robots to do
that first this is a pretty good
principle
[Music]
you